Finding Aid for George Wahr Sallade Papers 1952-1993
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
George Wahr Sallade papers 1952-1993
Sallade, George Wahr, 1922-
Ann Arbor, Michigan, attorney and local Democratic Party activist. Political files relating to his various campaigns for office (Ann Arbor city council, Michigan House of Representatives, U.S. Congress, and Michigan State Senate among others); papers relating to his service in the state House, 1955-1958; his activities with Washtenaw County, Michigan, and Second Congressional District Democratic affairs; also letters received from Lt. Lee M. Cecil, 1952-1954, describing his experiences as a soldier during the Korean War; and photographs.
86989 Aa 2
5 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was donated by George W. Sallade (donor no. 2287 ) beginning in 1987. Subsequent additions have been received.
The collection is open for research.
George Wahl Sallade, longtime Ann Arbor political activist, was born on November 16, 1922. He was educated at the University of Michigan and received an undergraduate degree in political science in 1943, and a law degree in 1961. A year later he became a practicing attorney in Ann Arbor.
Although Sallade was active in Michigan politics prior to 1950, it was in that year that he ran for and was elected to his first public office - that of Ann Arbor city councilman on the Republican ticket. He was elected city council president in 1953, and a year and a half later made a bid for higher office. He ran successfully and was elected state representative for the first district. He remained in the state legislature for six years, where he was known as a leader of the "Young Turks," a group of Republican legislators who tried to steer the party in a more liberal direction and often opposed party conservatives on matters relating to taxation and social programs.
Several years after he left the legislature, Sallade changed party affiliation and became active in the state Democratic party. He served as chairman of the Washtenaw County Democratic party from 1965-1969, and chairman of the Second Congressional District Democratic party, 1971-1975 and 1982-1983. Despite unsuccessful bids for the state senate in 1966 and 1970, the county prosecutor's seat in 1972 and 1984, and the United State Congress in 1982, Sallade remained (and remains) an active and influential party member. In 1984 he served as co-chairman of the Gary Hart presidential campaign in Michigan.
Outside of politics, Sallade has long been involved in the publishing business. In the 1950s he was general manager of Wahr's Bookstore in Ann Arbor, and he has been president of the George Wahr Publishing Company for many years. In the mid-1970s he published a short-lived, local morning newspaper, Good Morning Michigan, and in 1985 began to publish his own political newsletter, "Michigan Around and About."
The George Wahr Sallade papers, although limited in quantity (five linear feet), are of interest to the researcher of Michigan politics in the post-World War II era. They can be used to gather information on the "Young Turks," a group that in the 1950s foreshadowed the more moderate nature of the Michigan Republican party of the 1960s and 1970s. They provide insight into issues that were of concern to the Washtenaw County and Second Congressional District Democratic parties - including Vietnam, race, party reform, and the economy - in the troubled years of the late 1960s and early 1970s. The ideological positions of the two local parties, relative to the state party as a whole, can be determined by comparing the resolutions they passed with those of the state party and its platform. Finally Sallade's campaign files can be used to determine the issues of concern to the local electorate in the years in which he ran for public office. His 1968-1972 campaigns are fairly well documented from an issue standpoint (particularly his 1972 race for county prosecutor), and, therefore, can be used to determine whether and to what extent national events affected the conduct of state and county races. Sallade's papers should be supplemented by use of the Detroit News - Lansing Bureau index; the papers of Governor G. Mennen Williams; and those of the state central committees of the Michigan Democratic and Republican parties. All of these are at the Michigan Historical Collections. The Collections also has a complete run of both Good Morning Michigan and "Michigan Around and About."
The Sallade papers have been arranged in three series: Personal; Political: and Photographs.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor (Mich.). Common Council.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Politics and government.; Democratic Party (Mich.); Korean War, 1950-1953--Personal narratives, American.; Michigan. Legislature. House of Representatives.; Michigan--Politics and government--1946-1960.; Michigan--Politics and government--1961-1970.; Michigan--Politics and government--1971-1980.; Republican Party (Mich.); Washtenaw County (Mich.)
Subjects - Visual Material:
Activists.; Police--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Politics and government--1946-1960.; Politics and government--1961-1970.; Sallade, George Wahr, 1922-
Contributors:
Cecil, Lee M.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Personal
  Of most interest in the Personal series is the background material, which helps reconstruct his political career, and his speeches. The latter are from the 1950s, primarily those years in which he served in the state senate, and addressed such matters as industrial development in Washtenaw County, Eisenhower as a national leader, foreign affairs, education, civil rights, highways, mental health, labor, and the need for "positive government." There are folders of material on his publishing career, but they are limited in quantity and routine in nature (specific descriptions are provided in the contents list).
  - Background (Box 1)
  - Book Publishing 1953-1954 (Box 1)
  - Community Involvement 1960-1971 (Box 1)
  - Boy Scouts 1953 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence from Lee Cecil regarding his experiences in the Korean War, 1952-54 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, Personal, 1954-68 (Box 1)
  - Good Morning Michigan, 1973-1974 (Box 1)
    (mostly re staff and personnel policies, and advertising rates)
  - J.C.C.'s Man of the Year Award 1954 (Box 1)
  - Recommendations, 1992-93 (Box 1)
  - Sallade vs. Campus Inn, 1977-1978 (Box 1)
  - Speeches (handwritten) (Box 1)
  - Resume/ Biographical Material 1986 (Box 1)
  - Program-Dinner Honoring Sallade. Washtenaw Democrats 1987 (Box 1)
- Political
  The Political series is the largest of the three, and comprises 90 percent of the collection. It is arranged in five subseries: Campaigns; Elected Offices; Local Parties; National Democratic Party; and Miscellaneous.
  - Campaigns
    The Campaigns subseries is arranged by year and consists of correspondence, news releases, issues statements, and research files materials from most of Sallade's campaigns between 1953-1984 (there are no materials from his 1966 race for the state senate, and almost none on his 1956 and 1958 state house campaigns).
    - 1953
      - Ann Arbor City Council President (Box 1)
      - Post-Election Correspondence (Box 1)
    - 1954
      - State Representative, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - U.S. Representative: George Meader Campaign (Box 1)
    - 1955
      - Ann Arbor City Campaigns (Box 1)
    - 1956
      - State Representative (Box 1)
      - U.S. President (Box 1)
        (Washtenaw County Citizens for Eisenhower press release regarding Adam Clayton Powell visit)
    - 1958
      - State Representative (Box 1)
      - Other Campaigns (Box 1)
    - 1960
      - Lieutenant Governor (Box 1)
      - Nelson Rockefeller for U.S. President (Box 1)
    - 1961
      - Constitutional Convention Delegate (Box 1)
    - 1966
      - State Senator, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1968
      - Get-Out-The-Vote Drive, Washtenaw County (Box 1)
      - State Representative, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1970
      - State Senator, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1972
      - General (Box 1)
      - Prosecuting Attorney, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - Sallade vs. Secretary of State; Lawsuit re Primaries (Box 1)
    - 1980
      - Edward Kennedy Primary Campaign (Box 1)
    - 1982 (Box 2)
      - U.S. Congress, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - 1983-1984
      - Miscellaneous Campaign Material (Box 2)
      - Gary Hart Primary Campaign (Box 2)
      - Prosecuting Attorney (Box 2)
    - 1987-88
      - Gary Hart Primary Campaign (Box 2)
    - 1988
      - Presidential Campaign: "March 26 Coalition" (Box 2)
      - Presidential Campaign: Mario Cuomo (Box 2)
      - Conlin for Michigan Court of Appeals (Box 2)
    - 1990
      - James Blanchard Reelection (Box 2)
    - 1991
      - Fair Share School Financing Proposal (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous 1980-1988 (Box 2)
  - Elected Offices
    The Elected Offices sub-series is primary comprised of correspondence, and is arranged by office and year. There is a limited quantity of correspondence from Sallade's city council days which reflects in a general way his concerns as council president, but the bulk of this subseries is from the years 1955-1958, when he served as state representative. It is this portion of the collection that sheds light on the "Young Turks." Sallade corresponded with other "Turks" on various issues.
    - Ann Arbor City Council President 1953-1954, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - State Representative
      - Undated (Box 2)
      - 1955
        - General, 2 folders (Box 2)
        - Political (Box 2)
          (concerns "Young Turks" and their positions in party)
      - 1956
        - General Correspondence, 3 folders (Box 2)
      - 1957
        - Miscellaneous Constituent Correspondence (Box 2)
        - Constituent Correspondence, A-D, 4 folders (Box 2)
        - Constituent Correspondence, E-Z, 11 folders (Box 3)
        - Highway Construction (Box 3)
        - Miscellaneous Legislative Material (Box 3)
      - 1957-60
        - Press Clippings and Press Releases (Box 3)
      - 1958
        - Constituent Correspondence, January-June (Box 3)
        - Constituent Correspondence, July-December (Box 3)
      - 1958-1959
        - Constituent Correspondence (Box 3)
      - 1959
        - Constituent Correspondence (Box 3)
      - 1960-1961
        - Constituent Correspondence (Box 3)
  - Local Political Parties
    The Local Parties subseries is divided into materials related to the Second Congressional District Republican Party, the Second Congressional District Democratic party and the Washtenaw County Democratic party. Thereafter, the documents are arranged chronologically (falling mostly in the years of Sallade's chairmanships) and primarily consist of correspondence, convention materials (calls, minutes, resolutions, and some roll call votes), and the committee meeting minutes.
    - Second Congressional District, Republican Party 1954 (Box 3)
    - Second Congressional District Democratic Party
      - 1963-1968, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - 1971, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - 1972, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - 1973 (Box 3)
      - 1974 (Box 3)
      - 1983 (Box 3)
      - 1984 (Box 4)
      - 1985 (Box 4)
    - Washtenaw County Democratic Party
      - 1965-1966
        - Correspondence, A-Z, 10 folders (Box 4)
      - 1967-1970
        - County Convention, 4 folders (Box 4)
        - Correspondence, A-Z, 7 folders (Box 4)
        - Reapportionment; Wheeler vs. Washtenaw County Board of Supervisors (Box 5)
      - 1970
        - General (Box 5)
        - Convention (Box 5)
      - 1971
        - General (Box 5)
        - Convention (Box 5)
        - Reapportionment (Box 5)
      - 1972
        - General (Box 5)
        - Conventions, 2 folders (Box 5)
        - Reapportionment; Sallade vs. Washtenaw County Board of Supervisors (Box 5)
      - 1973
        - General (Box 5)
        - Convention (Box 5)
      - 1976 (conventions) (Box 5)
      - 1980 (Box 5)
      - 1981-1982
        - Reapportionment; Beals et al vs. Washtenaw County Reapportionment Commission, 2 folders (Box 5)
      - 1982
        - Convention (Box 5)
      - 1987
        - General; Dinner Honoring Sallade (Box 5)
      - 1980-91
        - Ann Arbor Democratic Party (Box 5)
      - 1992
        - General (Box 5)
    - Sallade vs. Secretary of State; Lawsuit re Primary Elections, 1972 (Box 5)
    - Michigan: Around and About; political newsletter, 1994-95 (Box 5)
  - National Democratic Party
    The National Democratic subseries is arranged chronologically and is comprised mostly of challenges to national policies on credentials and presidential preference. This subseries also includes correspondence and flyers for delegates to the 1984 national convention. There is one folder of Miscellaneous, which includes collected documents on the Michigan economy and tax reform, 1958-1964.
    - Credentials Challenge 1976 (Box 5)
    - Fairness Coalition 1983-1984 (Box 5)
    - National Convention 1984 (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Political Material 1957-1985 (Box 5)
    - Political Correspondence 1952-1970 (Box 5)
    - Political Material and Correspondence 1986-1992, 2 folders (Box 5)
- Photographs
  The Photograph series is small in size and is almost entirely photographs of Sallade alone or with unidentified groups. There is one set of negatives of informal portraits of Sallade.
  - Portraits; also informal photographs of Sallade alone and engaged in various political activities (Box 5)